<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Lavelo Triathlon Training</title>
    <link>https://blog.lavelo.es/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Lavelo Triathlon Training</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.151.2</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.lavelo.es/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Training Zones: From Z1 Recovery to Z5 VO2max</title>
      <link>https://blog.lavelo.es/posts/understanding-training-zones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.lavelo.es/posts/understanding-training-zones/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Walk into any triathlon training discussion, and you&amp;rsquo;ll hear athletes throwing around terms like &amp;ldquo;Zone 2,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;threshold,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;VO2max intervals.&amp;rdquo; But what do these zones actually mean? And more importantly, how do you use them to train smarter and race faster?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s break down the five training zones, what happens in your body during each, and how to use them strategically in your training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-training-zones-matter&#34;&gt;Why Training Zones Matter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Training zones exist because different exercise intensities create different physiological adaptations. Train too hard all the time, and you&amp;rsquo;ll overtrain and underperform. Train too easy all the time, and you won&amp;rsquo;t develop the specific fitness needed for racing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>70.3 vs Full Ironman: Which Distance Should You Target First?</title>
      <link>https://blog.lavelo.es/posts/70-3-vs-full-ironman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.lavelo.es/posts/70-3-vs-full-ironman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ve completed a few Olympic distance triathlons. You&amp;rsquo;re hooked. Now you&amp;rsquo;re eyeing the bigger distances, and the question looms: should you jump straight to a full Ironman, or build up through 70.3 first?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a decision that will shape the next 6-12 months of your training and racing, so let&amp;rsquo;s break down what you need to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-case-for-starting-with-703&#34;&gt;The Case for Starting with 70.3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training Volume Is Manageable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 70.3 requires roughly 8-12 hours of training per week at peak, compared to 12-18+ hours for a full Ironman. If you work full-time and have family commitments, fitting in 10 hours of training is challenging but doable. Fitting in 15-18 hours requires either significant sacrifices or an extremely understanding support system.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Base Phase Training: Building Your Aerobic Foundation</title>
      <link>https://blog.lavelo.es/posts/base-phase-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.lavelo.es/posts/base-phase-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The base phase is where champions are made, even if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel like it at the time. While other athletes are posting impressive interval sessions on Strava, you&amp;rsquo;re grinding through long, steady miles at what feels like a frustratingly easy pace. But here&amp;rsquo;s the truth: skip or shortcut your base phase, and you&amp;rsquo;ll pay for it later when it matters most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-base-phase-training&#34;&gt;What Is Base Phase Training?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Base phase is the foundation period of your training cycle, typically lasting 8-12 weeks. During this time, you&amp;rsquo;re primarily working in Zone 1 and Zone 2—that conversational pace where you could hold a discussion without gasping for air. For many athletes, especially those coming from running backgrounds, this feels painfully slow. That&amp;rsquo;s exactly the point.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
